"Can Goitrogens in Soy and Cruciferous Vegetables
Interfere with Thyroid Function?"
A healthy lifestyle
and preventable death?
What are the six
lifestyle factors
that collectively appeared
to cut the risk
of dying prematurely in half?
Not smoking,
not drinking heavily,
walking an hour a day,
sleeping around
seven hours a night,
not being overweight,
and the sixth is the one
dietary quality indicator
they used,
eating your greens.
Most people don't eat enough,
but is it possible
to eat too many?
I've talked about the risks
of getting too many oxalates
by eating too many
of certain greens,
like spinach and Swiss chard,
but what about
low-oxalate greens
like kale or collards?
This cabbage family
of vegetables
has natural
goitrogenic compounds
that can interfere
with thyroid function.
They can compete with our
thyroid's uptake of iodine.
But the answer is not to avoid
these super healthy foods,
but, rather, to get
enough iodine in our diet,
as I've talked about before.
There is, however,
an extreme threshold
we don't want to cross.
How much is too much?
From the New England
Journal of Medicine:
Coma Induced by
Ingestion of Raw Bok Choy.
A woman had been eating
about three pounds (1.30 kg)
a day, every day,
which means 15 cups (~450g)
a day is too much.
In the two months before
she was admitted
to the intensive care unit
in respiratory failure
with a diagnosis
of severe hypothyroidism,
she had consumed at least
1,000 cups of raw bok choy.
The reason raw was specified
is that the enzyme
that creates
these iodine-blocking compounds
when we bite into them
or chop them up
is rapidly deactivated
by cooking,
so we don't have
to worry as much
about eating
too many cooked crucifers.
There are also
goitrogenic compounds
in soybeans,
though there is
little evidence that
this presents a problem
for people with
normal thyroid function
who are getting enough iodine.
Now, if you have hypothyroidism
and are taking
thyroid hormone replacement,
soy may impair
the absorption of the drug.
But that is not unique to soy,
that's why
hypothyroidism patients
are told to take
their Synthroid
before breakfast,
or at least four hours
after a meal.
There have been over a dozen
randomized, controlled trials
on the effect of soy
on thyroid function.
Researchers found that soy
has no effect
on thyroid hormone levels,
but there was
a 10 percent elevation in TSH.
That may not mean anything
for people
with healthy thyroid glands,
but if your thyroid function
is already suboptimal
that could potentially
tip you over the edge.
About 1 in every 23 Americans
has what's called
subclinical hypothyroidism.
This is when our thyroid gland
continues to produce
normal levels
of thyroid hormones
but seems to have a more
difficult time than usual,
as evidenced by higher levels
of thyroid stimulating hormone.
Meaning our body
has to stimulate our thyroid
more than usual to produce
normal levels of hormones,
suggesting it may
be starting to fail.
Okay, so, 60 patients
with subclinical hypothyroidism
were randomized to eight weeks
of either the equivalent
of about two servings
of soy foods a day or nothing.
And six patients developed
overt hypothyroidism
while on the soy,
which is three times the rate
that would have been expected.
But the soy group
had a bunch of benefits,
like less insulin resistance,
lower inflammation,
and better blood pressures.
However, the thyroid findings
were so concerning
that the same research group
ran the study again,
but this time with
four times the dose of soy
and this time
there was no increase
in overt hypothyroidism.
What are we to make of all this?
Well, soy industry consultants
concluded that
these follow-up results
call into question
the initial findings.
I mean, if four times
the amount of soy
appeared to have no effect
then maybe the earlier
findings were a fluke.
But the study populations
were different.
In the later study,
the patients started out
with TSH levels that were
only barely elevated.
Normal levels go up
to 4.5 or 5,
so they were just over the line,
whereas in the earlier studies
they started out closer to 8,
meaning the patients
were further along
and therefore
potentially more sensitive.
If you follow people
with subclinical hypothyroidism
over time,
most patients who start out
with TSH levels over six
end up with overt hypothyroidism
within a decade,
but none of those
who started out
with levels between four and six
suffered the same fate.
So, if your TSH
is really elevated
it might be reasonable
to avoid soy,
but we'd need more research
to know for sure.